<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-25T02:34:49-05:00</updated><id>https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ROAM</title><subtitle>Research on Animal Movement - A graduate group from James Cook University</subtitle><entry><title type="html">State Space Models</title><link href="https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/2021/08/25/State-space-models.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="State Space Models" /><published>2021-08-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/2021/08/25/State-space-models</id><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">State-space models (SSMs) are useful in better predicting “true” values of a time series. They work by using simulations to make estimates through process and measurement equations. They are useful for inferring better tracks and hidden processes (i.e. behaviour), particularly when using less accurate data (e.g. Argos locations) and/or in the marine environment. A major limitation of using them is that they are hard to validate. Dr. Marie Auger-Méthé has recorded a helpful seminar (https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iS5xzcmhpW0) and written a review that is especially targeted towards students wanting to use SSMs: “A guide to state-space modeling of ecological time series” (Auger-Méthé et al. 2021, https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.02001). There are R tutorials included on how to fit SSMs and validate these models (our tutorial worked through Appendix 1).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Discussion Of Movement Ecology Framework Paper</title><link href="https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/2021/08/25/Discussion-of-movement-ecology-framework-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discussion Of Movement Ecology Framework Paper" /><published>2021-08-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/2021/08/25/Discussion-of-movement-ecology-framework-paper</id><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Over the last decades the study of movement ecology has faced many challenges, including the separation of animal movement research into taxonomic groups, lack of synthesis from different geographical regions and methodologies and sampling designs. Additionally, a unified framework for movement ecology studies was missing. With the aim to unify movement studies under a common conceptual framework, Nathan et al. 2008 proposed a movement ecology paradigm based on principle components of animal and plant movement. This includes how the organism moves, when and towards what destination the movement occurs, why the organism moves and the interaction of these components. Establishing a unified theoretical framework for animal movement studies, that synthesizes different aspects of individual movement and general theory of animal movement research has resulted in a well-known and well-cited manuscript which provides a great baseline for anyone interested in animal movement ecology. </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Movebank and MoveVis</title><link href="https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/tools/2021/08/16/Introduction-to-Movebank-and-Movevis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Movebank and MoveVis" /><published>2021-08-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/tools/2021/08/16/Introduction-to-Movebank-and-Movevis</id><author><name></name></author><category term="tools" /><summary type="html">In our fourth meeting, Kyana introduced Movebank - a free online database and platform for analysing animal movement data. We learnt how Movebank can be used to manage and archive our data, while giving users have the choice to make their data publicly available or not. Kyana showed us how to view and download publicly available data and introduced some of the analysis tools that are available on the online platform. In the second half of the session Emily demonstrated an example of MoveVis in R, a package for creating animations from tracking data. MoveVis is a visualisation tool that converts movement data into ggplot2 frames that can be rendered into a moving gif or video.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paranormal Pigeons</title><link href="https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/2021/08/10/Paranormal-Pigeons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paranormal Pigeons" /><published>2021-08-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/2021/08/10/Paranormal-Pigeons</id><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Meeting 15 – (Documentary screening) Paranormal Pigeons: Why do Birds Migrate by Real Wild</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How To Update The Website</title><link href="https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/2021/08/03/How-to-update-the-website.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How To Update The Website" /><published>2021-08-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-08-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://roam-jcu.github.io/roam-website/2021/08/03/How-to-update-the-website</id><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How to update the ROAM-JCU website</summary></entry></feed>